Jessica de Souza

Graduate Student Researcher - University of California San Diego jdesouza@eng.ucsd.edu -https://jessica-desouza.com - +1 858 302-1381

I joined the University of California San Diego as a Ph.D. student in January of 2020, where I joined the Ubiquitous Data & Computing Laboratory advised by Professor Edward Wang. At UCSD, my research focuses on solving problems in healthcare and enabling affordable and convenient personal health monitoring for patients with specific needs. More specifically, I am exploring new ways of measuring blood pressure using smartphones in adults that need an easy self-assessment of their heart conditions. Also, I am exploring a new project related to maternal and neonatal care to better understand and improve the breastfeeding experience for newborns using sound analysis and smart devices. My research interests involve ubiquitous computing and human-computer interaction for healthcare and how we can build accessible devices for people in need, especially for chronic illnesses. I am also interested in novel methods to get reliable biological data, either by using sensors, smartphones, or other devices. My technical background includes HCl and cognitive science, ubiquitous computing, sensing techniques, hardware development, embedded systems, data analysis, and signal processing.

Education History

Ph.D., Electrical and Computer Engineering University of California San Diego (UCSD), USA Jan. 2020 - Present Current GPA: 3.587

B.E., Telecommunications Engineering

Federal Institute of Santa Catarina (IFSC), Brazil

2014 - 2015

2013 - 2019

Exchange Student, Electrical and Computer Engineering University of Nevada, Reno, USA

Intensive English Language Center, High Advanced

2014

University of Nevada, Reno, USA

Employment History

Research

UC San Diego

Dr. Edward J. Wang Since January 2020

Graduate Student Researcher, Ubiquitous Data & Computing Lab

At the UDComp Lab, I am exploring new sensing techniques for biological signal acquisition using sensors, hardware development and programming in embedded systems. Some sensors I've worked with are: heart rate (PPG), pressure, thermal imaging, temperature probing, EMG.

Microsoft Research, Redmond

Dr. Sidhant Gupta and Dr. Jonathan Lester

Undergraduate Intern, Clinical Sensing and Analytics Group

May 2018 - August 2018

At MSR I created a novel wearable pulse sensing interface to improve cardiovascular health monitoring, with a noninvasive signal enhancement technique. I evaluated and compared it to existing wearable interfaces in a controlled study.

Federal Institute of Santa Catarina, Brazil

Research & Extension

Dr. Elen M. Lobato and Ramon M. Martins

June 2017 - December 2017

1. Research student I analyzed heart activities from a dataset involving myocardial infarction, arrhythmias, and healthy subjects, to predict abnormalities in cardiovascular exams.

2. Research student

Dr. Jorge H. Busatto Casagrande

June 2016 - December 2016

Developed a novel sensor for electrical and hydraulic monitoring in residential electric showers to reduce water and energy consumption.

Dr. Pedro Armando da Silva Junior

5. Extension student

February 2016 - June 2016

Taught middle and high school students the concepts of embedded systems and basic robotics. Worked towards increasing the number of students in the STEM field.

University of Nevada, Reno

Dr. Yantao Shen

Research student, Bioinstrumentation and Automation Lab

June 2014 - July 2015

At UNR I worked on the "E-Braille" project, collecting bioimpedance from the fingertip to find correlations between finger applied force and the bioimpedance, for an electrical stimulation closed-loop system.

Industry.

AQTech Power Prognostics, R&D Team

Software Development Analyst

July 2019 - November 2019

I worked with Analog Devices' WirelessHART technologies for a wireless sensor network for an energy power plant. Implemented protocols and coded in firmware and intermediate level (C/C++) for specific applications. I also started and managed the testing table process for large-scale device manufacturing.

IMEX Medical Group

Equipment Maintenance and Installation Intern

March 2019 - July 2019

At IMEX I've provided corrective and preventive maintenance in digital X-rays, ultrasounds, mammography, and CT. I also did remote access to install and correct bugs in x-ray systems, exam visualization software, and hospital database. I have gained experience with the following brands for hardware and software: Terarecon, IRAY, Barco, Hologic Dimensions, Alpinion Medical Systems.

Honors, Awards, and Grants

- o 2017 Second place at the IFSC Innovative Ideas Contest, Brazil. 10,000.00 BRL grant.
- o 2017 Best extended abstract at the VIII Computer on the Beach. UNIVALI, Brazil.
- o 2015 Outstanding First-Year Student In Chinese. University of Nevada, Reno, USA.
- o **2014** Scholarship Holder of CAPES (Improvement Coordination of Higher Education Personnel), in the Brazil Scientific Mobility Program (BSMP).

Technical and Personal skills

- o Programming Languages: Familiar with: C, C++, Python, Java, Android, PowerShell, HTML, CSS.
- Industry Skills: Signal processing, analog and digital circuits, wireless communication & RF, computer networks, embedded systems (hardware & firmware), human-computer interaction, prototyping and testing devices, medical imaging equipment.
- **Personal Skills:** Written and oral communication, project management, activity and environment organization, problem-solving, leadership, creativity, eager to learn.
- o Softwares: MATLAB, Multisim, Eagle, Visual Studio, Quartus ModelSim, GIT, Linux, Proteus Circuit, AutoCAD.
- Relevant Courses: Linear algebra, cognitive science foundations, foundations for future user interfaces, humancentered computation for health, embedded system design project, human-centered programming, programming for data analysis, introduction to biophysics, principles of biomedical imaging, medical devices and interfaces.

Extra-curricular activities

- o UDComp Lab Spring break research experience. Eagle tutorial for undergraduates. UC San Diego. 2021.
- o Volunteer at ACM international joint conference on pervasive and ubiquitous computing (UBICOMP). Online. 2020.
- Presented several inspirational talks at my undergraduate university about: engineering careers, opportunities during college, exchange programs, why is it important to learn a new language, experiences as a woman in STEM. Between 2015 and 2018.
- o Attended the Annual Ideagen UN Empowering Women Girls 2030 Summit. United Nations NY. 2018.
- o Organizing committee, IEEE Latin American Symposium on Circuits and Systems. Florianopolis, Brazil. 2016.

References

- o Edward Wang, Ph.D., UC San Diego.
- o Sidhant Gupta, Ph.D., Microsoft Research.
- o Samuel Heiderscheidt, Imex Medical Group.
- o Roberto Wanderley da Nóbrega, Ph.D., Federal Institute of Santa Catarina.